Guide to the Dept. of Political Science Records, 1930-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Dept. of Political Science records 1930-1982
Duke University. University Archives
Duke University. Dept. of Political Science
4.5 linear feet Extent: 5400 Items
The Department of Political Science was established in 1934 and continues today with both undergraduate and graduate programs. The collection contains correspondence, clippings, course materials, applications, honors theses, and departmental papers.
UA.25.33.0001
Language: Material in English
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Collection is open for research.
Provenance
The Dept. of Political Science Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer between 1966 and 1997.
Historical Note
The Department of Political Science was established in 1934 and currently includes thirty-one permanent faculty members as well as a number of distinguished adjunct and visiting faculty. The department, which in recent years has consistently ranked among the top ten graduate political science programs in the country, offers students a broad intellectual approach to the discipline, a long-standing commitment to excellence in both teaching and research, and a lively and collegial intellectual community.
Collection Overview
Collection contains departmental files, Honors-Master's Program theses, prize-winning term papers, miscellaneous announcements, memoranda, booklets, and budget and salary recommendations, from the Political Science Department. The materials range in date from 1922 to 1993, with the bulk from 1962 to 1980.
The collection is arranged into the following series: Theses and Papers, General Files, Graduate School, and Course Material. Each series is arranged alphabetically. The bulk of the collection is miscellaneous files relating to departmental affairs and applications and appointments. Major subjects are R. R. Wilson and Robert S. Rankin.
Subject Headings
Duke University. Dept. of Political Science; Rankin, Robert S.
Contents of Collection
- Theses and Papers, (.5 boxes)
  Contains Honors Theses, paper by a professor, prize winning papers, and general student papers.
  - Honors Theses (Box 1)
    - Caire, Constance A. "An Interpretation of Executive Power: Abraham Lincoln as Commander-in-Chief," 1963 (Box 1)
    - Corder, Carol. "The National Law Tradition and its Validity to the 20th Century," 1960 (Box 1)
    - Cupps, D. Stephen. "The Founding Fathers' Conception of the American Executive," 1963 (Box 1)
    - Gager, Stewart Douglas. "The Impact of the Federal Bureau of Investigation on our Federal System of Government," 1962 (Box 1)
    - Gecker, Judith. "Julius Kambarage Nyerere: the Making of a Nation," 1964 (Box 1)
    - Hall, Hines H. "The Executive Power and the Evolving Structure of the Defense Department Organization," 1963 (Box 1)
    - Hottle, Warren Paul. "Metropolitan Government in the National Capital Area," 1962 (Box 1)
    - Levison, Sanford V. "A Critique of the Theory of Nuclear Deterrence," 1962 (Box 1)
    - Logan, Emmelyn S. "The United States Supreme Court, the Political Process and Federalism," 1962 (Box 1)
    - May, James N. "The Social Democratic Part of Germany and German Reunification: A Selective Study," 1964 (Box 1)
    - Rouse, Margaret C. "Executive Power and the Tariff: The Reciprocal Trade Agreement Program," 1963 (Box 1)
    - Strange, John H. "Lasswell and His Critics," 1960 (Box 1)
    - Towle, Patricia. "Executive Power in Relation to the Regulatory Commissions," 1963 (Box 1)
    - Vickery, Raymond E. "The Effects of United States Radical Difficulties on America's Relations with Africa," 1964 (Box 1)
    - Weir, Michael. "President Truman's Recognition of Israel: A Case Study in the Power of the Executive to Grant Recognition," 1963 (Box 1)
  - Prize-Winning Papers
    - Burde, Howard. "President Harry S. Truman..." Evans Prize, 1982 (Box 1)
    - Lambros, Mitchell. "The Politics of Using Economic Incentives..." Proctor and Gamble Award, 1982 (Box 1)
  - Professor Paper
    - Sindler, Allan P. "Youth and the American Negro Protest Movement: A Local Case Study of Durham, NC," 1960-1964 (Box 1)
  - Student Papers
    - Aosono, Erwin. "Promoting America's Image and Interests," 1982 (Box 1)
    - Kuzil, Lea A. "The Non-Russian Nationalities of the U.S.S.R." (Box 1)
    - Herr, Richard A. "The Failure of Federalism in New Zealand," 1971 (Box 1)
    - Hatting, Steve. "Private Rights and the Public Interest," 1973 (Box 1)
    - Slocum, Gail L. "Menstrual Politics," 1981 (Box 1)
- General Files, (1.5 boxes)
  - Applications for Positions -- J-R, 1931-1940 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions -- A-L, 1949-1951 (Box 1)
  - Applications for Positions -- A-F, 1935-1940 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions -- G-I, 1931-1940 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Positions -- S-Z, 1931-1941 (Box 2)
  - Applications for Scholarships and Assistantships (Box 2)
  - Arbitration - R.S. Rankin Harriet and Henderson Cotton Mills (Box 2)
  - Budget, 1964-1969 (Box 2)
  - Budget, 1969-1971 (Box 2)
  - Canada - Committee on Commonwealth Studies (Box 2)
  - Chair: Presidential Libraries [Nixon Library], 1981 (Box 2)
  - Clippings Re: Department of Political Science (Box 2)
  - Committee on Government Research and Training in the South (Box 2)
  - Courses Approved (Box 2)
  - Conference on International Legal Studies at Institutions in the Southern Region of the United States -- Held at Duke University, April 22-23, 1955 (Box 2)
  - Correspondence Concerning Job Openings for Graduate Students, 1958-1959 (Box 2)
  - Department Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Departmental and Graduate Recommendations (Box 2)
  - Departmental Information (Box 2)
  - Departmental Items and Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Departmental Records (Box 2)
  - Drake, Thomas M. (Box 2)
  - Faculty Reogranization (Box 2)
  - German Training Program, 1949-1950 (Box 2)
  - Grade Distribution Reports (Box 2)
  - Grade Distribution Statistics, Fall Semester, 1940-1941 (Box 2)
  - Honors Program (Box 2)
  - Journal of Politics - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Litchfield, Edward H. (APSA) - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - Material for Undergraduate Bulletin (Box 2)
  - Memos Re: Department of Political Science (Box 2)
  - Military Status Members of Department of Political Science (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Department Papers and Correspondence (1 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Department Papers and Correspondence (2 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Department Papers and Correspondence (3 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Department Papers and Correspondence (4 of 4) (Box 2)
  - Mr. Don R. Beeson - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - The North Carolina Finishing Company (Box 2)
  - Ph.D. Candidate Final Exam Nominations, 1941 (Box 2)
  - Political Science, 1943-1944 (Box 2)
  - Political Science, 1944-1945 (Box 2)
  - Political Science Department Group Meetings (Box 2)
  - Professor R. Taylor Cole, 311 Library (W) (Box 2)
  - Professor Robert S. Rankin - Correspondence (Box 2)
  - R. R. Wilson (Box 3)
  - Recommendations Correspondence (1 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Recommendations Correspondence (2 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Recommendations Correspondence (3 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Resumes/CVs (Box 3)
  - Round Table - American Political Science Association (Box 3)
  - Self-Study Report of the Department of Political Science (Box 3)
  - South Carolina Studies (Box 3)
  - Southern Research Agencies (Box 3)
  - Student Lists (Box 3)
  - University Council (Box 3)
  - War Bond Drive, 1944 (Box 3)
- Graduate School, (.5 boxes)
  - Admissions and Appointments (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Admissions and Appointments (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Applications (Box 3)
  - Appointments, 1949-1952 (Box 3)
  - Committees (Box 3)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
  - Graduate Council (Box 3)
  - Graduate Seminars Summaries and Announcements (Box 3)
  - Inquiries (Box 3)
  - Material for Graduate School Bulletin (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (1 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous (2 of 2) (Box 3)
  - Programs of Graduate Students (Box 3)
  - Report of Various Colleges (Box 3)
  - Lilly Endowment Fund, 1957-1960 (Box 3)
- Course Material, (.5 boxes)
  - Political Science courses 21 and 22, c. 1934-1948 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 61 and 62, c. 1934-1941 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 101 and 102, c. 1930-1940 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 111, 125, 136, 164, 211, c. 1936-1941 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 242, 244, 246, 291, c. 1938-1941 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 225-229, c. 1935-1943 (Box 3)
  - Political Science courses 250-251: World Politics, April, 1961, Dr. K. B. Sayeed (Box 3)
  - Course Offerings and Exam Schedules, 1943-1944 (Box 3)
  - Enrollment in Courses Statistics (Box 3)
  - Exams and Course Descriptions, 1935-1936 (Box 3)
  - Final and Make-Up Exams, 1941 (Box 3)
  - Honors Class - Second Semester, 1934-1935 (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Course and Program Materials (1 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Course and Program Materials (2 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Miscellaneous Course and Program Materials (3 of 3) (Box 3)
  - Political Science 202 Senior Seminar (Box 3)
  - Subcommittee on Pre-Med Course (Box 3)
  - Syllabi, Japanese Civilization, 1954-1955 (Box 3)
  - Report - Teaching the Beginning Course in Political Science, 1959 (Box 3)